Alexey Lutsai: For many people, game ports are an anachronism from the early 00's. Surely you have tried projects ported from consoles to PCs, and it was
Aleksei Luțai: Pentru mulți oameni, portările de jocuri sunt un anacronism din anii 2000. Cu siguranță ați încercat proiecte portate de pe console pe PC și nu a fost
not too cool. Nowadays the term "multiplatform" is used more often. A game comes out everywhere at once. And thats it.
prea cool. În zilele noastre, termenul „multiplatformă” este folosit mai des. Un joc apare peste tot în același timp. Și asta e tot.
But imagine one of the major native PC games, and specifically Gothic,
Dar imaginați-vă unul dintre cele mai importante jocuri native pentru PC, și anume Gothic,
has just been ported to Nintendo Switch, and console players will finally be able to join in on the greatness. What's going on?
tocmai a fost portat pe Nintendo Switch, iar jucătorii de consolă vor putea în sfârșit să se alăture fenomenului. Ce se întâmplă?
Why and who needs it? How are games ported in general? Is a port always a literal port or does it sometimes extend the game itself?
De ce și cine are nevoie de asta? Cum sunt portate jocurile în general? O portare este întotdeauna o portare la propriu sau uneori extinde jocul în sine?
Today we'll deal with it. I talked to the guys from the St. Petersburg studio Elverils, which deals with ports of games. For example,
Astăzi ne vom ocupa de asta. Am vorbit cu băieții de la studioul Elverils din Sankt Petersburg, care se ocupă cu porturi de jocuri. De exemplu,
Larian games on Mac and iPad. They've just released Baldur's Gate 3. Or you may know them from the iPad port of Original Sin 2.
Jocuri Larian pe Mac și iPad. Ei tocmai au lansat Baldur's Gate 3. Sau poate îi cunoașteți de la portarea lui Original Sin 2 pentru iPad.
They were originally the first open St. Petersburg office of Larian. They also make ports of Piranha Bytes games,
Inițial au fost primul birou deschis al Larian din Sankt Petersburg. Ei fac, de asemenea, portări ale jocurilor Piranha Bytes,
like Risen on Switch and Mac, Elex 2 on Mac. They were the ones who released the updated version of the first Gothic on Switch, which
cum ar fi Risen pe Switch și Mac, Elex 2 pe Mac. Ei au fost cei care au lansat o versiune actualizată a primului Gothic pe Switch, pe care
which we will discuss. By the way, THQ has already announced a second part for Switch, and it's also being made by the guys at Elverils. If you're into this format,
o vom discuta. Apropo, THQ a anunțat deja partea a doua pentru Switch, iar aceasta este realizată tot de băieții de la Elverils. Dacă vă place acest format,
please be sure to give it a like so I can keep it going.
nu uitați să îl susțineți cu un like, ca eu să îl pot continua.
Thank you in advance! One of the most common questions I get asked by subscribers when they meet me is "How do I get into game development?"
Vă mulțumesc anticipat! Una dintre cele mai frecvente întrebări pe care mi le pun abonații atunci când mă întâlnesc întâmplător este: „Cum intru în
and what is the best field of study to choose. And here's how things are: artists, producers, musicians, even screenwriters
gamedev?” și ce direcție să ia. Și lucrurile stau așa: artiști, producători, muzicieni, chiar și scenariști
it's not hard to find, but game designers are rare. The industry is literally screaming about it in every interview and podcast. You may need
nu sunt greu de găsit, dar designerii de jocuri sunt rari. Industria strigă literalmente despre asta în fiecare interviu și podcast. Un proiect mare
a dozen such specialists for a big project.  For example, combat system designer, minigame designer,
poate avea nevoie de o duzină de astfel de specialiști. De exemplu, un designer de sisteme de luptă, un designer de mini-jocuri,
a level designer, a system designer who makes the rules in the game world work.  There's a lot to choose from, and
un designer de nivel, un designer de sistem care face ca regulile din lumea jocului să funcționeze. Există o mulțime de opțiuni, iar
I would recommend learning at Contented in the "game designer" course. Because it's one of the biggest schools,
eu v-aș recomanda să studiați această profesie la Contented, la cursul de „game designer”. Pentru că este una dintre cele mai mari școli,
that teaches design in all its forms. The program includes more than 40 practical assignments so that you can immediately
care predă designul în toate formele sale. Programul include mai mult de patruzeci de exerciții practice, astfel încât să puteți imediat
apply your knowledge and build your portfolio. The outcome of the course is a project of your own game. The training will last 12
să vă puneți în aplicare cunoștințele și să realizați un portofoliu. Rezultatul cursului este un proiect de joc propriu. Formarea va dura 12
months, and at the end of the course you will be confident working with Unity, Unreal and Game Maker. You will master
luni, iar până la final veți cunoaște bine Unity, Unreal și Game Maker. Veți stăpâni
Unity Bolt, Blueprints, and Perforce visual programming tools that you need to build your prototypes.
Unity Bolt, Blueprints și instrumentele de programare vizuală Perforce de care aveți nevoie pentru a vă construi prototipurile.
You'll analyze the mechanics of your favorite games and discover them from a new perspective. There will also be three gamejams in the program,
Veți analiza mecanica jocurilor voastre preferate și le veți descoperi dintr-o nouă perspectivă. Programul va include, de asemenea, trei game jam-uri,
so you can practice teamwork. Classes are 4 to 8 hours long
astfel încât să puteți exersa munca în echipă. Cursurile durează între 4 și 8 ore
per week. If you don't have time for something, you can move the homework deadlines and even freeze the course so you can come back to it later.
pe săptămână. Dacă nu aveți timp pentru ceva, puteți să mutați termenele pentru teme și chiar să înghețați cursul, astfel încât să vă puteți întoarce la el mai târziu.
The course is supervised by Kirill Zolovkin, a game designer with twenty years of experience. He has worked at Wargaming and My.Games. By the way, he recently had
Cursul este supervizat de Kirill Zolovkin, un designer de jocuri cu douăzeci de ani de experiență. El a lucrat la Wargaming și My.Games. Apropo, recent, el
a release of his game called "Gripper", which was recognized by Shuhei Yoshida, head of Sony's indie division. Your age and experience are not important, they will teach you everything
a lansat Gripper, care a fost recunoscut de Shuhei Yoshida, șeful diviziei indie a Sony. Vârsta și experiența ta nu contează, ei te vor învăța totul
from scratch, and the career center will help you get a job or find freelance clients. Newcomers to the profession
de la zero, iar centrul de carieră vă va ajuta să obțineți un loc de muncă sau să găsiți clienți independenți. Nou-veniții în profesie
earn from 80,000 rubles, and middles from 190,000. Contented students start
câștigă de la 80.000 de ruble, iar cei medii de la 190.000. Elevii mulțumiți încep
to work from the sixth month of school. And by the way, the school will give you a certificate on the basis of
să lucreze din a șasea lună de formare. Și apropo, școala vă va da un certificat pe baza
State License 041164. And also, after registering for the course, you will get a training module on neural networks and access to a closed Telegram bot with 40 of their
Licenței de stat 041164. De asemenea, după înregistrarea la curs, veți primi un modul de instruire privind rețelele neuronale și acces la botul Telegram închis cu patruzeci de
varieties. You will understand Mid Journey, Pixel App and all kinds of Chat GPT that will help you in working on your
varietăți ale acestora. De asemenea, veți obține acces la Mid Journey, Pixel App și tot felul de Chat GPT-uri care vă vor ajuta în activitatea voastră
projects. So if you love games and are ready to get involved in an industry hungry for game designers, then sign up at the link
la proiecte. Așadar, dacă adori jocurile și ești pregătit să te implici într-o industrie dornică de designeri de jocuri, atunci înscrie-te la acest link
in the description or QR code. And my promo code "LVCAI" will be 45% off.
din descriere sau cu codul QR. Și cu codul meu promoțional „LVCAI” va fi o reducere de 45%.
Lutzai: What are some of the things that have changed that are visible at the 1st glance?
Luțai: Care sunt lucrurile care s-au schimbat și care sunt vizibile cu ochiul liber?
Platon Fomichev: At the 1st glance - UI, of course. The map section appeared. Then we tried to revive some mechanics from Gothic.
Platon Fomicev: Cu ochiul liber - interfața de utilizator, desigur. A apărut o secțiune de hartă. Apoi am încercat să reînviem unele mecanici din Gothic.
In particular, I think, throwing items.
În special, în opinia mea, aruncarea de obiecte.
[Platon Fomichev. Elverils Technical Director] Well the music, yes, the music, the positional sound. Gothic was very famous for its exactly
[Platon Fomicev. Director tehnic Elverils] Ei bine, muzica, da, muzica, sunetul pozițional. Gothic a fost foarte faimos pentru sunetul său
positional sound, I mean, well music is okay, but then there was EAX. When we were making Gothic,
pozițional, adică muzica este în regulă, dar apoi a apărut EAX. Când am făcut Gothic,
we were all very surprised at how positional sound is now dead as a class.
am fost cu toții foarte surprinși de faptul că sunetul pozițional este acum mort ca domeniu.
We did some reverb. It's off by default because
Am făcut niște reverberații. Sunt oprite în mod implicit deoarece
it wasn't to everyone's liking. We'll probably finish it some more. There's also reverb
nu au fost pe placul tuturor. Poate le vom mai îmbunătăți. Există și reverberație
in the game, so the game has a physical model of sound. It's trying to follow that
în joc, adică jocul are un model fizic al sunetului. Încearcă să urmeze această
sound library that it had before. Yeah, the sound is completely rewritten as well, because the sound library
bibliotecă de sunet pe care o avea înainte. Da, sunetul este complet rescris, de asemenea, pentru că biblioteca de sunet
is long gone. The font. Yeah, the font's also changed. We made it so that it reads well on the screen both
a dispărut de mult. Fontul. Da, fontul s-a schimbat. Am făcut în așa fel încât să se citească bine pe ecran atât
when the Switch is in your hand and when the Switch is in the TV. Diego: "We'll meet in the Old Camp."
atunci când ai Switch-ul în mână, cât și atunci când Switch-ul este în televizor. Diego: „Ne întâlnim în tabăra veche”.
Lutzai: Gothic is 20 years old now. There are a lot of archaic decisions in the game.
Luțai: Gothic este deja vechi de 20 de ani. Există o mulțime de decizii arhaice în joc.
[Reinhard Pollice. THQ Nordic Product Director]. I tried the game and it feels like the console came out like 20 years ago.
[Reinhard Pollice. Director de produs la THQ Nordic]. Am încercat jocul și se simte ca și cum consola ar fi apărut acum 20 de ani.
That's a solution that older players will love.
Soluția aceasta va fi pe placul jucătorilor mai vechi.
But it seems like the younger guys won't understand. So what audience was the port of the game created for?
Dar se pare că cei mai tineri nu vor înțelege. Deci, pentru ce public a fost creată portarea jocului?
Reinhard: the goal was to bring Gothic back to the people who remember it. Who
Reinhard: цель состояла в том, чтобы вернуть Готику людям, которые помнят её. Которым
would like to play this deep RPG again, but in a handheld.
ar dori să joace din nou acest RPG profund, dar pe un dispozitiv portabil.
This is a game for those who prefer detailed simulation.
Acesta este un joc pentru cei care preferă simularea detaliată.
We never intended to make a modern version for the sake of hooking people who, for example,
Nu a fost niciodată intenția noastră să creăm o versiune modernă de dragul de a atrage oameni care, de exemplu,
playing Zelda or something like that on Switch. In many ways, these controls work better than the keyboard
joacă Zelda sau ceva similar pe Switch. În multe privințe, acest sistem de control funcționează mai bine decât tastatura
and mouse on PC. Of course, we haven't done everything perfectly, but we'll try to fix that.
și mouse-ul pe PC. Desigur, nu am făcut totul perfect, dar vom încerca să o rezolvăm.
We know that Gothic has a large community, so our goal is to give them what they want.
Știm că Gothic are o comunitate mare, așa că scopul nostru este să le oferim ceea ce își doresc.
Lutzai: A couple years ago in my video about Gothic
Luțai: Cu câțiva ani în urmă, în videoclipul meu despre Gothic
I said that it has such specific controls because it was originally designed for the gamepad.
am spus că are controale atât de specifice deoarece a fost proiectat inițial pentru gamepad.
And to be honest, I was a bit of a liar at the time. Indeed, there was such information on the Internet, but it was no
Și sincer, am fost un pic confuz la momentul respectiv. Într-adevăr, astfel de informații au fost găsite pe Internet, dar nu a existat nicio confirmare
confirmation to this fact.
neechivocă a acestui fapt.
I say "fact", although I was basing it on my subjective impressions.
Am spus „fapt”, deși mă bazam pe impresiile mele subiective.
But here's what I learned from Gothic Classic's UX designer Konstantin.
Dar iată ce am învățat de la Konstantin, designerul UX al Gothic Classic.
Lutzai: You know, despite the fact that in the video I said about the console control, I mean there was basically the feeling of fighting and a lot of things were
Luțai: Știi, în ciuda faptului că în videoclip am spus despre controlul de pe console, vreau să spun că a existat practic senzația de a te lupta și o mulțime de lucruri
essentially done on the keyboard. And it felt like the gamepad would fit here perfectly. But lets say I said this back then
au fost făcute în esență pe tastatură. Și am simțit că gamepad-ul s-ar potrivi perfect aici. Dar să spunem că am spus asta atunci
and found some confirmations in different sources. But I'm not 100 percent sure that's what it was.
și am găsit unele confirmări în diferite surse. Dar nu sunt sută la sută sigur că asta a fost.
[Konstantin Timofeev. UI/UX developer Elverils] Well I found in the code traces of what was being developed. There were such modules, there were such workarounds. Basically, I took some of it from there.
[Konstantin Timofeev. Dezvoltator UI/UX Elverils] Ei bine, am găsit indicii în cod despre ceea ce se dezvolta. Au existat astfel de module, au existat astfel de dezvoltări. Practic, am preluat o parte de acolo.
Lutzai: Almost like a random guess, but it turns out there is such information.
Luțai: Aproape ca o bănuială întâmplătoare, dar se pare că există astfel de informații.
Konstantin: I really liked their original idea that they made all the controls in the game through action plus direction.
Konstantin: Ceea ce mi-a plăcut cu adevărat la ideea lor originală este că au realizat toate comenzile în joc prin acțiune plus direcție.
And I had a hypothesis that, yeah, we have a combat system based on this,
Și am avut o ipoteză că, da, avem un sistem de luptă bazat pe această
interaction, but they probably intended for there to be dialog on this
interactivitate, dar cel mai probabil intenționau să existe dialoguri pe aceasta
and some other features. So all the features were supposed to be on this. And when we had already opened the alpha builds, we looked at them,
și alte funcții. Așadar, toate funcțiile ar fi trebuit să fie pe aceasta. Și când am deschis build-urile alfa, ne-am uitat la ele,
and that hypothesis was confirmed. Because they have just down there on the bottom right, they've specifically showed Ctrl, Shift buttons,
această ipoteză a fost confirmată. Pentru că au chiar acolo jos, în dreapta jos, au introdus în mod specific butoanele Ctrl Shift,
the arrows and they'd sign what the actions on them should be done.
săgețile și arătau acolo ce acțiuni ar trebui făcute pentru ele.
They literally had everything there following the same logic. What are these buttons? Why did they choose them?
Ei aveau literalmente aceeași logică în spatele a tot. Ce sunt aceste butoane? De ce le-au ales?
Yeah, it's really a console solution. This is us going back to the first gamepads,
Da, este într-adevăr o soluție pentru consolă. Acest lucru ne duce înapoi la primele gamepad-uri,
where there were two buttons, jump, attack, cross.
unde existau două butoane, săritură, atac, cruce.
By the way, as it was on the arcade machines. I mean it's absolutely such an old world idea.
La fel ca dispozitivele arcade, de altfel. Adică, este o idee atât de veche.
But it's an idea that's unkillable. Because when we started doing Motion Control,
Dar această idee este imbatabilă. Pentru că atunci când am început să facem Motion Control,
we found that it was a concept that was easy to put on it. Because Motion Control is just four directions,
am constatat că conceptul a fost ușor de integrat. Pentru că Motion Control are exact patru direcții,
that you use in the air. So you can press two buttons. We have an idea about
pe care le faci în aer. Deci, poți apăsa două butoane. Avem o idee
to make pure classic Gothic controls as an option. That's exactly the kind of "classic"
pentru a face din controalele clasice din Gothic o opțiune. Ăsta e exact tipul de
Motion Control, that is, one Joy-Con, waving in the air, to get through the whole game.
Motion Control clasic, adică un singur Joy-Con, fluturând în aer, pentru a trece prin întregul joc.
Interaction with inventory, in dialogs. Anything can be done.
Interacțiunea cu inventarul, în dialoguri. Totul poate fi făcut mai scurt.
Lutzai: No, you heard the man right! They've really brought Joy-Con Motion Control into the port. Now it's practically a game for all type of players on Nintendo now.
Luțai: Nu, ați auzit bine! Ei au adus într-adevăr Joy-Con Motion Control în port. Acum este practic un joc pentru toate tipurile de jucători de pe Nintendo.
[Gleb Shelkoudenko. Elverils Game Designer] I have a major question: why is there Motion in Gothic 1? Who came up with it? Who put that in?
[Gleb Șelkoudenko. Game Designer Elverils] Am o mare întrebare: de ce există Motion în primul Gothic? Cine l-a inventat? Cine l-a implemetat?
Gleb Shelkoudenko: Actually I still keep asking myself the same question. Because in general, it was a completely experimental initiative that our
Gleb Șelkoudenko: De fapt, încă mă mai întreb același lucru. Pentru că, în general, a fost o inițiativă complet experimentală, pe care
programmer Alexander realized simply because he could. There was a willful decision to show this
programatorul nostru Aleksandr a implementat-o pur și simplu pentru că a putut. A existat o decizie voluntară de a o arăta
to our chief on the publisher's side, and he liked it quite unexpectedly.
șefului nostru din partea editorului, iar lui i-a plăcut în mod neașteptat.
And he said: "you can make it a feature now." And we didn't breathe out
Iar el a spus: „Acum puteți face din asta o funcționalitate”. Și nu am răsuflat
easily at all, because it was already a bit of a challenge.
deloc ușurați, pentru că existau deja unele dificultăți.
Lutzai: what can I do here with Motion? Gleb: Actually, all interaction with Motion's is limited only by the weapon. It is enough, basically,
Luțai: ce pot face cu Motion aici? Gleb: De fapt, toată interacțiunea cu Motion-urile este limitată doar de armă. Un pic este suficient, în general,
I was initially very skeptical of the idea. When the goal was to get it to some sort of near playable state.
am fost inițial foarte sceptic cu privire la această idee. Când a fost trasată sarcina de a o aduce la o stare aproape jucabilă.
Simply because in my experience, I can't think of a single hardcore game where Motion controls
Pur și simplu pentru că, din experiența mea, nu mă pot gândi la un singur joc hardcore în care sistemul de control Motion
looked like a really relevant feature, rather than something like: let us just show you how our technology works.
să pară o caracteristică cu adevărat relevantă și nu ceva de genul: hai doar să vă arătăm cum funcționează tehnologia.
Lutzai: There's a gamepad, it's like it's always been there. And basically Motion probably
Luțai: Există un gamepad, e ca și cum ar fi fost mereu acolo. Și, în principiu, Motion este probabil
makes sense in this system where you do these swinging things around. But the only thing is that it's very conventional anyway.
logic în acest sistem, unde totul este atât de împrăștiat. Dar singurul lucru este că mișcările sunt oricum foarte convenționale.
Gleb: It's interesting that when we started to test it in practice, it turned out that the dynamics of Gothic gameplay in general, and combat in particular,
Gleb: Interesant, când am început să verificăm acest lucru în practică, sa dovedit că, în general, dinamica gameplay-ului Gothic, și lupta în special,
it oddly enough, and in general, fits into this concept. And it even works in some places.
destul de ciudat, în general, se încadrează în acest concept. Și chiar funcționează în unele locuri.
At least if you know exactly how it interacts.
Cel puțin dacă știi exact cum interacționează.
Lutzai: This Motion is specific too, as the normal controls here! Kind of hardcore. [Laughter] I can't hit it!
Luțai: Este la fel de specific Motion ca și controalele normale făcute aici, de asemenea, destul de hardcore. [Râde] Nu pot s-o lovesc!
Глеб: Gleb: Basically, any even the most shitty implemented Motion can be simply... Lutzai: You try it.
Gleb: În principiu, orice mișcare, chiar și cea mai prost realizată, poate fi pur și simplu... Luțai: Încearcă tu.
Gleb: justify that... Lutzai: The game is too hardcore. Gleb: Yeah, we've paid tribute to that.
Gleb: pentru a justifica acest lucru. Luțai: Jocul este prea hardcore. Gleb: Da, i-am adus un omagiu.
Lutzai: Yes, keeping continuity to the original gameplay and its unfriendliness.
Luțai: Da, menținând continuitatea gameplay-ului original și ostilitatea acestuia.
Lutzai: Did you modernize the combat in any way? Changed maybe the pace, the balance?
Luțai: Ați modernizat lupta în vreun fel? Ați schimbat ritmul, echilibrul, poate?
Konstantin: We are working on the combat and we will continue to work on it. Right now we are working on the focus, so we have a normal
Konstantin: Lucrăm la luptă și vom continua să facem acest lucru. Chiar acum lucrăm la focalizare, astfel încât să existe o focalizare automată normală
autofocus and targeting. Because players are complaining and basically we need to refine it.
și țintirea să fie normală. Pentru că jucătorii se plâng și în principiu trebuie să o perfecționăm.
We've done a mix of classic combat
Am făcut un amestec între lupta clasică
and the modern one. That is, you can attack by clicking the enemy and, by pressing the action, you can fence.
și lupta modernă. Adică, puteți ataca făcând clic pe inamic și, apăsând pe butonul de acțiune, vă puteți feri.
We've made it so that you can both stagger and jump back. So we've split that moment.
Am făcut în așa fel încât să puteți atât să vă dezechilibrați, cât și să săriți înapoi. Așa că am împărțit acel moment.
It used to be kind of merged, meaning you could only jump back. The fencing mechanics is developed,
Înainte era un fel de îmbinare, ceea ce însemna că puteai sări doar în spate. Mecanica de eschivă este dezvoltată,
and it was even more developed in the alpha build. I, for example, have a dream of bringing back side tumbling from the alpha build.
iar în build-ul alfa a fost dezvoltată și mai mult. Eu, de exemplu, am un vis de a aduce înapoi rostogolirea laterală din buildul alfa.
Now, people will probably say "well you're already making Dark Souls out of Gothic". But actually Gothic was like that from the beginning.
Acum, oamenii vor spune probabil: „Ei bine, veți face Dark Souls din Gothic”. Dar, de fapt, Gothic a fost așa de la început.
So the battles were dynamic and that's what it is now, these kind of left-to-right drifts,
Adică, luptele erau dinamice și asta se întâmplă acum, cu aceste mișcări de la stânga la dreapta,
these ridiculous steps - back then they were full-fledged rolls.
acești pași ridicoli - pe atunci erau tumbe în toată regula.
[Irina Starygina. QA-engineer at Elverils] The work on Gothic's controls was very curious and interesting. It took quite a good amount of time.
[Irina Starîghina. inginer QA Elverils] Lucrul la sistemul de control al Gothic a fost foarte curios și interesant. A durat destul de mult timp.
We've been surfing the fan sites for this game.
Am navigat pe site-uri ale fanilor acestui joc.
We collected comments, we analyzed it all. We made a test control system, we sent it to the Germans.
Am colectat comentarii, am analizat totul. Am realizat un sistem de control de testare, l-am trimis germanilor.
They looked at it, touched it with their hands, gave their opinion. After that, they
S-au uitat la el, l-au mânuit, și-au dat cu părerea. După aceea, ei
did a meeting of old players who like Gothic, and they'd listen to what they thought about the controls.
au organizat o adunare a celor vechi care îndrăgesc Gothic, și au ascultat opiniile lor cu privire la sistemul de control.
So we worked with all that feedback and tried to incorporate it.
Așa că am lucrat cu toate răspunsurile și am încercat să-l includem.
Луцай: And these "old-players" wanted the controls to be "old-like" too? Or what did they want?
Luțai: Și acești „jucători-vechi” voiau ca sistemul de control să fie și el în stilul vechi? Sau ce voiau?
Irina: They wanted to keep the identity of the game.
Irina: Ei voiau să se păstreze identitatea jocului.
I mean, if you love something, you don't like it to be twisted and completely turned into something else.
Adică, dacă îndrăgești ceva, nu-ți place când este sucit și transformat în cu totul altceva.
When we were discussing what kind of controls to do and what it should even look like, we had debates about how to fit this "forward and action" thing in.
Când discutam despre ce fel de sistem de control să facem și cum ar trebui să arate, am avut discuții despre cum să integrăm conceptul de „înainte și acțiune”.
I was talking about how the modern users shouldn't have to suffer so much, and how everything should be with one button.
Punctul meu de vedere a fost că utilizatorul modern nu ar trebui să sufere atât de mult și că totul ar trebui să se întâmple cu un singur buton.
We argued and argued, and then we thought there should be two control systems. So now you're playing the more modern version, like
Am dezbătut și am dezbătut, iar apoi am ajuns la concluzia că ar trebui să existe două sisteme de control. Așa că acum jucați versiunea mai modernă, adică
a little bit simplified, which allows you to focus on the story.
una ușor simplificată, care vă permite să vă concentrați pe poveste.
Lutzai: It's simplified, right? [Laughs] Okay, which one is more Hardcore then?
Luțai: Este simplificată, nu? [Râsete] Bine, care este mai hardcore atunci?
Irina: In the original Gothic, we have three or four keys that you have to press to do one action. And I used to get very angry.
Irina: În originalul Gothic, avem trei sau patru taste pe care trebuie să le apeși pentru a face o acțiune. Și asta mă enerva foarte tare.
Lutzai: So you had an impact on that? Irina: We have a team, we all give our opinion and everyone listens to it.
Luțai: Deci tu ai influențat acest demers? Irina: Avem o echipă, cu toții ne exprimăm părerea și toată lumea o ascultă.
Lutsai: How did they convey to you this task: "Make it so that the old guys like it anyway, and make it mean and hardcore, don't simplify it"?
Luțai: Cum ți-au comunicat această sarcină: „Fă-l în așa fel încât jucătorilor vechi să le placă oricum, și să fie dur și dificil, nu-l face ușor”?
Gleb: It even came to such absurd situations, when the chief from the publishing house side says,
Gleb: S-a ajuns chiar la situații atât de absurde, când șeful din partea editorului a spus
that you have to do it like this. "Like this" means literally as it was there 23 years ago.
că trebuie făcut așa. „Așa” înseamnă literalmente cum a fost acum 23 de ani.
I write him back with a two and a half page tirade of why it shouldn't be done that way, giving him 150 arguments why.
Îi răspund cu o tiradă de două pagini și jumătate în care îi explic de ce nu ar trebui făcut așa, dându-i 150 de argumente.
But in the end, he's like, "no." Okay, okay.
Dar în cele din urmă, el a spus „nu”. Bine, bine.
So we keep the [magic] wheel, we keep the three-button berry picking.
Deci păstrăm roata [pentru magie], păstrăm cele trei butoane pentru culesul fructelor de pădure.
Lutzai: So basically there was a temptation to kind of "improve the game"? I mean, to make it up to modern standards of some kind?
Luțai: Deci, practic, a existat o tentație de a „îmbunătăți jocul”? Adică, de a-l face să corespundă standardelor moderne?
Gleb: People probably don't like Gothic as much as they like who they were,
Gleb: Oamenilor s-ar putea să nu le placă Gothic la fel de mult pe cât le plăcea ceea ce erau
when they played the game. And what they encountered when they played it.
atunci când l-au jucat. Și ce au întâlnit atunci când l-au jucat.
Relying on some advice, recommendations, wishes in the major aspects without the presence of which
Să te bazezi pe unele sfaturi, recomandări, dorințe în aspecte majore, fără de care
Gothic turns into a literally different game - that's welcome, that's me all the time, but clinging to the
Gothic se transformă într-un joc literalmente diferit - este binevenit, așa sunt și eu tot timpul, dar să te agăți de
preserving every single minor feature, even if it frankly didn't work like much even then,
conservarea fiecărei caracteristici minore, chiar dacă, sincer vorbind, nici atunci nu funcționa foarte bine,
and even more so 20-odd years later. It's like it's not really rational, at least in my mind.
ba chiar mai mult de atât după 20 și ceva de ani. Parcă nu e chiar rațional, cel puțin în mintea mea.
Konstantin: UX of games went a little bit the other way. Overall, I don't see that the UX has gotten more user-friendly.
Konstantin: UX-ul jocurilor a luat-o puțin pe un drum greșit. În general, nu văd ca UX-ul să fi devenit mai ușor de utilizat.
It's gotten more complicated because of this logical fragmentation.
A devenit mai complicat din cauza acestei fragmentări logice.
So you're just shown some random button that's responsible for this. Another random button that's responsible for this.
Deci pur și simplu ți se arată un buton aleatoriu care e responsabil pentru asta și un alt buton aleatoriu care e responsabil pentru cealaltă.
There's no logic. Often I don't get it, what did they actually base the logic of this arrangement of buttons on?
Nu există nicio logică. De multe ori nu înțeleg. Pe ce au bazat de fapt logica acestui aranjament de butoane?
What did they want to get out of it? I mean, there's no complete picture.
Ce au vrut să obțină din asta? Adică, nu există o imagine de ansamblu.
Gothic's approach was cleaner, more logical, and ingenious in that,
Abordarea Gothic a fost mai curată, mai logică și mai ingenioasă în sensul că
That you don't even have to memorize button names. You have the four directions. You always know about the four directions.
nu trebuie să memorezi nici măcar numele butoanelor. Ai patru direcții. Întotdeauna știi care sunt cele patru direcții.
For example, you're interacting with some object. What would it mean "forward", better to say "upward"?
De exemplu, interacționezi cu un obiect. Ce ar însemna „înainte”, sau mai bine zis „în sus”?
What would mean "backwards"? What would "left-right" mean? Your brain will tell you, it's pure association.
Ce ar însemna „înapoi”? Ce ar însemna „stânga-dreapta”? Creierul tău îți va spune. E vorba doar de asociere.
It doesn't have a name [The scheme says: "L + A - all interactions with the world!"]. You don't need to look at the legend to figure out which button is responsible for what.
Nu are un nume [Schema zice: „L + A - toate interacțiunile posibile cu lumea!”]. Nu trebuie să te uiți la legendă ca să te prinzi care buton e responsabil pentru ce.
And it's also different in different places for different things. Gothic didn't have any of that. You just click to interact,
Și e, de asemenea, responsabil pentru lucruri diferite în locuri diferite. Gothic nu avea nimic din toate astea. Doar apeși pe butonul de interacțiune,
and then you associatively choose forward, backward, left, right. Forward is something you have to do, apparently, to use.
iar apoi alegi asociativ: înainte, înapoi, stânga, dreapta. Înainte este ceva ce trebuie să faci, aparent, să folosești.
Back is something to undo, to throw away. Left to right is some options, meaning you're switching something.
Înapoi înseamnă să anulezi ceva, să arunci ceva. Stânga-dreapta reprezintă unele opțiuni, adică schimbi ceva.
Your brain is already telling you everything. But there's a high entry threshold there because it's not universally accepted. Here's the thing.
Creierul tău îți spune deja totul. Dar există un prag de intrare ridicat pentru că nu e ceva obișnuit. Iată care e treaba.
It's new at the time, and even now I would call it new. I mean, it's just not mainstream yet, and maybe it won't be.
Era ceva nou la acea vreme, și chiar și acum l-aș numi nou. Adică, nu a devenit încă general acceptat, și poate că nu va deveni.
But if it was, there wouldn't be all these problems of how to do this or how to do that.
Dar dacă ar fi fost, nu ar mai fi existat toate aceste probleme despre cum să facem asta sau cum să facem aia.
As you may have noticed, I'm shooting in a new location. Yes, I've finally set up my own studio, where
După cum poate ați observat, filmez într-o locație nouă. Da, mi-am amenajat în sfârșit un studio separat unde
I don't interfere with anyone's life and work with my filming and streaming. But it takes a long time to decorate the studio and Im lazy to go somewhere
nu interferez cu viața și munca nimănui cu filmările și transmisiunile mele. Dar mi-e prea lene să petrec mult timp decorând studioul și
to shop. So I ordered a lot of stuff on Megamarket, because there's a cool one-click delivery option there.
mergând la cumpărături. De aceea am comandat o mulțime de lucruri pe Megamarket, pentru că există o opțiune cool acolo.
For household appliances and electronics there's an awesome cashback up to 60% with bonuses from Sber "Spasibo".
Pentru electrocasnice și electronice există un cashback minunat de până la 60% cu bonusuri de la Sber „Spasibo”.
I got myself two of these RGB lamps for atmosphere, a light filter on the lens,
Mi-am luat două dintre aceste lămpi RGB pentru atmosferă, un filtru de lumină pentru obiectiv,
some surge protectors, and an external 500GB SSD for the camera so that the footage can be written directly to it. And then of course,
câteva dispozitive de protecție la supratensiuni și un SSD extern de 500 GB pentru cameră, astfel încât imaginile să poată fi înregistrate direct pe cameră. Și, desigur,
I'm going to need a coffee machine again. It's not like I'm bringing mine from home. Anyway, the basket was
voi avea nevoie din nou de un filtru de cafea. Nu e ca și cum l-aș aduce pe al meu de acasă. În total, coșul a ajuns la
18709 rubles, and I'll get 2147 rubles back in cashback.
18709 ruble, iar 2147 de ruble îmi vor fi returnate prin cashback.
And this is, for example, a healthy pack of coffee for a month. And you can pay up to 99% with bonuses
Și acesta este un pachet sănătos de cafea pentru o lună, de exemplu. Și puteți plăti până la 99% din prețul de achiziție
of the purchase price. And if you order goods at Megamarket with SberPrime and SberPrime+ subscriptions, you will get
cu bonusuri. Și dacă comandați bunuri la Megamarket cu abonamente SberPrime și SberPrime +, puteți obține
you'll get even more cashback. Shipping is free, by the way. And like I said, there's click-to-deliver. And what it is: ordering
și mai mult cashback. Apropo, livrarea este gratuită. Și, așa cum am spus, există livrare pe clic. Și cum se desfășoară: comanda
will first be delivered to a Megamarket partner, and you get a notification. Then you call a courier, and he will deliver the order in a period of time from
va fi mai întâi adusă la un partener al Megamarket, iar tu vei primi o notificare. Apoi suni un curier, iar acesta va livra comanda în
15 minutes. And if it's the first time you're ordering something, enter my promo code "ОСЕНЬТЕХНИКА".
15 minute. Și dacă comandați ceva pentru prima dată, introduceți codul meu promoțional „ОСЕНЬТЕХНИКА”.
And get a discount of 3,000 rubles for an order of 10,000 rubles or more. In general, to
Și obțineți o reducere de 3.000 de ruble pentru o comandă de 10.000 de ruble sau mai mult. În general,
buy with comfort and profit go to my link in the description.
pentru a cumpăra confortabil și cu profit, accesați link-ul meu din descriere.
Lutzai: Would you say that the version that you're working on now is
Luțai: Ați spune că versiunea la care lucrați acum este, într-un fel,
an improved version of what it was, and it's a better state of Gothic than players once played it?
o versiune îmbunătățită a ceea ce a fost, și este o versiune mai bună a Gothic decât cea pe care au jucat-o jucătorii cândva?
Platon: There are a lot of people who watch modern media and who read forums. They like to say:
Platon: Există atât de mulți oameni care urmăresc presa modernă și care citesc forumuri. Le place să spună:
"They took a game from twenty years ago, ported it to Switch, no 60 fps, no raytracing,
„Au luat un joc vechi de 20 de ani, l-au portat pe Switch, fără 60 fps, fără raytracing,
no shadows. We have modders who can do everything better. What were they doing? It could have been done in, like, a month."
fără umbre. Sunt modderi care au făcut toate astea. Ei ce-au făcut? Ar fi putut fi făcut în, gen, o lună.”
Well, that's completely untrue. Because people just don't represent,
Ei bine, asta e complet neadevărat. Pentru că oamenii pur și simplu nu au idee
what it is to really port a modern game. First of all, it's old code.
ce înseamnă să portezi cu adevărat un joc modern. În primul rând, este un cod vechi.
This is C++ code. It's great, it still works, but it's
E cod C++. Este minunat și încă funcționează, dar a fost
was written for the 32-bit Microsoft Visual Studio 6.0 platform. It's not a super secret. Basically, it's how it is.
scris pentru platforma Microsoft Visual Studio 6.0 pe 32 de biți. Nu e un super secret. Practic, asta e
And most of the old games were written for the old Visual Studio because it was a Windows project. And if it's
realitatea. Și majoritatea jocurilor vechi sunt scrise pentru vechiul Visual Studio, deoarece a fost un proiect Windows. Și dacă era
was a Windows project, then it was using Windows technology. And hardcore Windows technology. And the very first Windows
un proiect Windows, atunci se folosea tehnologia Windows. Mă refer la tehnologie Windows hardcore. Iar prima tehnologie Windows
technology that you can call 0 is definitely DirectX technology. DirectX 6 or 7, I honestly don't rememeber right now.
pe care o puteți numi 0 este cu siguranță tehnologia DirectX. DirectX 6 sau 7, sincer nu-mi amintesc acum.
But it's the DirectX Fix pipeline, so called. So there were no shaders back then. But there was a Fix pipeline,
Dar este pipeline-ul DirectX Fix, denumit astfel. Adică, nu existau shadere în acele zile. Dar exista pipeline-ul Fix,
which was fun, too. So what that means is that putting just Gothic on Switch
care era și el interesant. Deci, ceea ce înseamnă asta e că pur și simplu să transferi Gothic pe Switch
is impossible. It just won't run. Because Switch doesn't know anything about the Fix pipeline. It's had a shader
e imposibil. Pur și simplu nu va rula. Pentru că Switch nu știe nimic despre pipeline-ul Fix. Va sta în pipeline-ul
pipeline for a long time. This is where you have to, yeah, pay tribute to the German
shadere mult timp, apoi „Salut”. Într-adevăr, trebuie să aplaudăm punctualitatea
punctuality. Here they had everything in the repository just like 20 years ago.
germană. Ei au avut totul în repozitoriu cam acum 20 de ani.
Nothing was lost. Nothing was lost, no assets were lost, everything was in place.
Nu s-a pierdut nimic. Nimic nu a fost pierdut, nicio resursă nu a fost pierdută, toate erau la locul lor.
So we took code that was almost a hundred years old and started working with it.
Din acest motiv, am luat codul care era vechi de atâția ani și am început să lucrăm cu el.
Lutzai: Is this essentially reconstructing the game from scratch? Or a transfer of, shall we say, one environment to another?
Luțai: E asta, în esență, o reconstrucție a jocului de la zero? Sau o trecere, să spunem, dintr-un mediu în altul?
Plato: Let's put it this way. Everything that needed to be rejuvenated in terms of code is rejuvenated.
Platon: Să o spunem așa. Tot ceea ce trebuia reînnoit în ceea ce privește codul este reînnoit.
The game has been brought up to the latest C++ realities. Everything that needed to be rewritten in terms of graphics - rewritten.
Jocul este adaptat la cele mai recente caracteristici C++. Tot ceea ce a trebuit să fie rescris în materie de grafică - rescris.
So completely new rewritten. Everything else about the rest of it, which is
Vreau să spun, rescris complet. Tot restul, care reprezintă
primarily scripts, gameplay. Well it is, of course, updated to the controller. Overall
în primul rând scripturi, gameplay. Ei bine, este, desigur, adaptat la controller. Atmosfera
the feeling of the world, the change of day and night, the weather, the behavior of NPCs - everything is left as it is.
generală a lumii, schimbarea zilei și a nopții, vremea, comportamentul NPC-urilor - totul este lăsat așa cum era.
Lutzai: In general, it turns out that the Gothic we love came out not quite the way it was intended. The guys at Elverils for their
Luțai: De fapt, se pare că Gothic pe care îl iubim nu a ieșit chiar așa cum s-a dorit. Băieții de la Elverils au studiat
port studied the alpha build of the game and found a couple of interesting solutions that didn't make it to the release.
build-ul alfa al jocului pentru portarea lor și au găsit acolo câteva soluții interesante, care nu au ajuns să fie lansate.
What else you think was cool in the alpha that didn't make it to the release game,
Ce altceva crezi că a fost grozav în versiunea alfa și care nu a ajuns în varianta finală a jocului
and you suddenly dug this up and you thought, "Wow! That's cool. It's a shame they didn't do that."
și pe care ai descoperit-o brusc și te-ai gândit, „ Uau! Asta e mișto. Ce păcat că nu au făcut asta”.
Konstantin: I really liked the mechanics of throwing objects,
Konstantin: Mi-a plăcut foarte mult mecanismul de aruncare al obiectelor,
because it was originally designed for stealth. It was conceived of you throwing some kind of food to the beasts,
pentru că a fost conceput inițial pentru stilul de furișare. A fost conceput ca tu să arunci niște mâncare animalelor,
they react to it, they move out of the path, you go through. But the thing that struck me the most, of course, was when you kill some kind of
ele reacționează la asta, se dau din calea ta, iar tu mergi mai departe. Dar lucrul care m-a marcat cel mai mult, desigur, a fost atunci când ucizi o
mob, you take its body, and you carry it to a much larger mob to distract it with that body. We have
creatură, îi iei cadavrul și îl duci la o creatură mult mai mare pentru a o distrage cu acel cadavru. Avem un
an item throwing mechanic. It's about to come out with an update, but nothing changes from those item throws.
mecanism de aruncare a obiectelor. Va veni cu următoarea actualizare, dar nu schimbă nimic la sistemul vechi de aruncare a obiectelor.
But in alpha it was one of those cool mechanics.
Dar în alfa a fost una dintre acele mecanici mișto.
The best port is the one that adds something to the game so you know that, yes, there's your favorite game out there
Cea mai bună portare este cea care adaugă ceva la joc, astfel încât să știi că, da, ai jocul tău preferat
on your favorite platform. But here's some features on the other platform that your original game didn't have.
pe platforma ta preferată. Dar aici, pe cealaltă platformă, există unele funcționalități pe care jocul tău original nu le avea.
And you're wondering what it would be like if I was going through with some new features.
Și începi să te întrebi: „Cum ar fi dacă merge mai departe cu unele funcționalități noi?”.
Well in this case, we have the opportunity to implement what Piranha Bytes wanted to implement, but they
Ei bine, în acest caz avem posibilitatea de a implementa ceea ce Piranha Bytes a vrut să implementeze, dar
didn't have enough time, for example. There's modifications, the famous zGamepad.
nu au avut suficient timp, de exemplu. Există modificări, renumitul zGamepad.
Lutzai: Speaking of which, did you go to them, did you look into those modifications?
Luțai: Apropo de asta, i-ați abordat, ați analizat aceste modificări?
Konstantin: Of course, yes. We looked at their modification first thing.
Konstantin: Bineînțeles că am făcut-o. Primul lucru pe care l-am făcut a fost să ne uităm la modificarea lor.
Well, I can say that they have gone exactly the way of this modernization. Just like this, closer to the modern player.
Ei bine, pot să vă spun că au mers pe această cale de modernizare. Exact așa, mai aproape de jucătorul modern.
But that would, in our case, in our task, break continuity with the original in terms of
Dar în cazul nostru, în sarcina noastră, ar rupe continuitatea cu originalul în ceea ce privește
the implementation of the action + direction mechanics. Their combat is done differently - it already violates this whole logic.
mecanismul de „acțiune + direcție”. În cazul lor, lupta se face diferit - încalcă deja această logică.
I'm on the contrary inclined to have more of these mechanics in the game. So that players get a sense of how flexible it is.
Dimpotrivă, tind să doresc mai multe astfel de mecanisme în joc. Astfel încât jucătorii să simtă cât de versatil este.
Lutzai: In addition to the strange controls by today's standards, Gothic had a specific interface design that wasn't very comfortable.
Luțai: În afară de sistemul de control ciudat pentru standardele actuale, Gothic avea un design specific al interfeței care nu era foarte confortabil.
It was decided to be reimagined from scratch. For example, there's a feature that may be sacrilegious to hardcore gamers
S-a decis să se reimagineze de la zero. De exemplu, există un lucru, care poate e o blasfemie pentru jucătorii hardcore,
thing - a convenient menu of maps. Well, and in addition to that, a lot of things were redrawn under the new experience of use, which made the game more accessible.
- un meniu convenabil de hărți. Ei bine, și în plus față de asta, multe alte lucruri au fost redesenate cu noua experiență de utilizare în minte, care a făcut jocul mai accesibil.
For example, there is now a modernized equipment menu with a rubric. And it's easy to see what the hero is wearing.
De exemplu, există acum un meniu de echipament modernizat cu o rubrică. Și e ușor de văzut ce poartă eroul.
Plus a more or less convenient magic wheel.
Plus o roată pentru magie mai mult sau mai puțin la îndemână.
Why did you go for such a minimalistic UI style? I've heard the feedback, by the way.
De ce ați ales un stil de interfață atât de minimalist? Apropo, am auzit feedback-ul.
Some people said that it reminds me of MMO stuff like that. Although, on the other hand, I kind of understand that
Unii oameni au spus că le amintește de lucruri din MMO-uri într-un fel. Deși, pe de altă parte, îmi dau seama că,
I mean, it's pretty much in keeping with the aesthetic. Somehow it even reminds me of Part 2's interface.
în general, se încadrează destul de bine în estetică. Cumva, chiar îmi amintește de interfața celei de-a doua părți.
[Sofia Demina. UI/UX Elverils Artist] We chose the second part first, because of the commitment to the series and all that.
[Sofia Demina. artist UI/UX Elverils] Am ales mai întâi partea a doua, ca un fel de angajament față de serie și toate cele.
Gothic is a very brutal game, again you can see that very well in the interface of the second part.
Gothic e un joc foarte brutal, iar lucrul acesta poate fi văzut clar în interfața celei de-a doua părți.
It's so brutal. It gives you exactly what you need, no more, no less. There was an idea to add a switcher
E atât de dur. Îți oferă exact ceea ce ai nevoie, nici mai mult, nici mai puțin. A existat o idee de a adăuga un buton de comutare
between the interfaces so that maybe somebody would want to go more minimalist, somebody would want to go more fantasy-like.
între interfețe, astfel încât poate cineva să dorească să o păstreze pe cea mai minimalistă, iar altcineva să o păstreze pe cea mai sofisticată.
Lutzai: How was the communication built? How do you get tasks set for you? And in what form do you bring them in?
Luțai: Cum a fost structurată interacțiunea dintre voi? Cum vi se dau sarcini? Și în ce formă le furnizați?
Sofia: I was doing different searches, experimenting with how I could present information to the player,
Am făcut diverse căutări, am experimentat cu modul de prezentare a informațiilor pentru jucător,
whether it suits the client. And generally doing research on the project, reading fan forums.
dacă se potrivește clientului. Și, în general, am făcut cercetări asupra proiectului, am citit forumurile fanilor.
I've probably read everything there is to read. I watched videos, walkthroughs, I mean gameplay: what the player complains about, what they don't.
Am citit probabil tot ce era de citit. Am urmărit videoclipuri, walkthrough-uri, adică gameplay: de ce se plânge jucătorul, de ce nu.
Obviously, I was turning this on at X2 speed, but I had a pretty massive study like that in there.
Evident, am făcut asta la viteza X2, dar am făcut niște cercetări destul de ample.
More on fan patches and reviews of those fan patches.
Mai multe despre patch-urile fanilor și recenzii ale acestor patch-uri ale fanilor.
It's not enough to do something from a fan, you also have to see how other fans reacted to it: they like it, they don't like it.
Nu e suficient să faci ceva pentru un fan, trebuie să vezi și cum au reacționat alți fani: le place, nu le place.
Irina: There's another thing, you probably noticed. Lutzai: We have two weapons, two weapons to choose from,
Irina: Mai e un lucru, poate ați observat. Luțai: Avem două arme, două arme din care poți alege,
before you could only have one. So that's kind of convenient, actually. Irina: Yeah, I mean we've always had the standard, this is the long-range and short-range
înainte puteai alege doar una. E, în general, convenabil. Irina: Da, adică, întotdeauna am avut acest standard - o armă pentru distanță și o armă corp la corp
weapon. Now, if you like to swing swords, you can pick two cool blades of your favorite and carry them around.
Acum, dacă îți place să mânuiești săbii, poți alege două săbii mișto și să le porți cu tine.
Lutzai: Didn't the guys mind that? Olds who wanted to keep that authenticity, some complexity.
Luțai: Против этого ребята не были? Олды, которые хотели сохранить всё-таки эту аутентичность, некоторую сложность.
Irina: Well, you can probably afford it, especially since we discuss, test and practice all these things.
Irina: Ну маленькую дерзость себе наверное можно позволить, тем более мы все такие вещички обсуждаем, проверяем, отрабатываем.
Lutzai: Tell me how you came up with the idea to make two weapons,
Luțai: Расскажи как к вам пришла идея сделать два оружия,
because it's really more convenient, it's what was missing, and it expands the tactical possibilities.
потому что это действительно удобнее, это то чего не хватало, и расширяет тактические возможности.
Konstantin: It's just inconvenient when in the inventory there are some individual slots highlighted. You have to look
Konstantin: Просто неудобно когда в инвентаре там подсвечены какие-то отдельные слоты. Ты должен смотреть
what you have selected, what you don't have selected. The equipment window was needed. And in that window,
что у тебя выбрано, что не выбрано. Окно снаряжения напрашивалось. И в этом окне у нас получалось,
we have one slot for melee combat and one for long-range. So this is the ranged slot, it's going to be
что один слот у нас будет на ближний бой, другой на дальний. Получается вот этот слот на дальний бой, он будет
and it's gonna be in the hotbar, and it's gonna be in your eye all the time. So if you're not, let's say, an archer, a crossbowman,
фигурировать еще и в хотбаре, и он будет всё время мозолить глаза. То есть если ты, допустим, не лучник, не арбалетчик,
you will always have an ampty slot. I thought it looks not so good.
у тебя всё время будет этот пустой слот. Мне показалось это вообще некрасивым.
That's when the thought was born: what if they were independent? It doesn't matter what you keep in that slot.
И тогда и родилась мысль: а что если они будут типонезависимыми? Неважно что ты держишь в этом слоте.
So we finally implemented that, and it turned out to be really convenient. I've seen on streaming shows how a streamer approaches
Ну и мы в итоге это реализовали, и получилось действительно удобно. Я видел на стримах как стример подходит
to the stone golem. He pulls out his sword and then realizes what a mistake that was and remembers he still has his hammer.
к голему каменному. Он достаёт меч и потом понимает какая это была ошибка, и вспоминает что у него ещё есть молот.
He gets knocked back, he's got a little bit of health left. He quickly grabs the hammer from the second slot, starts fighting off the golem.
Его откидывает, у него там чуть-чуть здоровья осталось. Он быстренько выхватывает молот из второго слота, начинает отбиваться от голема
and defeats it. That's the game situation, I think it justifies the decision.
и побеждает его. Вот такая игровая ситуация, мне кажется, она оправдывает это решение.
Lutzai: And roughly how many iterations did your suggestions go through?
Luțai: А сколько примерно итераций прошли твои предложения?
Sofia: There were about 6 or 8 iterations. They were global rethinks of the interface. I wouldn't say they were super successful.
Sofia: Где-то 6 или 8 было итераций. Это были глобальные переосмысления интерфейса. Не сказала бы что они были суперудачные.
I like that we decided to mostly focus on the original because I like that hard brutality of the original.
Мне нравится, что мы решили по большей части ориентироваться на оригинал, потому что мне нравится эта жёсткая брутальность оригинала.
But in our iterations, we've tried separating the information so that it's more easily presented, or let's say
Но в своих итерациях мы пробовали разделять информацию, чтобы она удобнее подавалась, или допустим
could free up the middle of the screen. Some windows close it when there's no pause active in the game.
освобождать середину экрана. Некоторые окна его закрывают, когда паузы активной в игре нет.
Lutzai: Why did you decide not to keep the vertical interface?
Luțai: Почему ты решила не оставлять вертикальный интерфейс?
Sophia: Honestly, I love those bars in the inventory. I really wanted to keep them, but the client
Sofia: Честно говоря, мне нравятся эти столбики в инвентаре. Я очень хотела их оставить, и заказчик попросил что хорошо,
but he would like the inventory to be like in Gothic 2. But the second Gothic is inconvenient
но он хотел бы, чтобы инвентарь был как во второй Готике. Но вторая Готика неудобна тем,
is that it's just a bunch of stuff. I mean, at least the first one is structured. So we combined
что там всё скопом лежит. То есть первая она хотя бы структурирована. Ну и мы совместили
the structuring from the first one and this big inventory from the second one.
структурирование из первой и вот этот большой инвентарь из второй.
I was really afraid that the players wouldn't like this innovation, it seemed kind of wild to me.
Я очень боялась, что игрокам не понравится такое нововведение, мне оно казалось диковатым.
Honestly? I didn't play Gothic when the time was right. There were other favorite games.
Честно говоря? я не играла в Готику когда было подходящее время. Были другие любимые игры.
Maybe I'm just less familiar with it, but I thought this brutal limitation was kind of cool.
Возможно, я просто хуже её понимаю, но мне казалось, что вот это брутальное ограничение - это же прикольно.
You're walking, and you have a bag. There are items in the bag, and you can't get to all of them at once. And it's like
Ты идёшь, и у тебя есть сумка. В сумке есть предметы, и ты не до всех можешь сразу добраться. И это такое как бы
limitation. You have to keep track of the management of the items: some to take away, some to leave, and so on.
ограничение. Тебе приходится следить за менеджментом предметов: какие-то убирать, какие-то оставлять и так далее.
I like that roughness.
Мне нравится эта шероховатость.
Working with the fonts - that was certainly something creepy.
Работа со шрифтами - это было, конечно, нечто жуткое.
Lutzai: Why? Were they somehow hard to get them out of there to rework?
Luțai: А почему? Их как-то сложно было оттуда достать, чтобы переработать?
Sofia: Well, how can I tell you... We have six, I think, languages in there to start with.
Sofia: Ну как тебе сказать... Для начала у нас там шесть, кажется, языков.
Thank goodness I didn't have to work with characters for Chinese. So many characters in every language.
Слава Богу, мне не нужно было работать с иероглифами для китайского. Очень много символов в каждом языке.
At the very least let's take English and Russian, that's already 60 pieces there, roughly speaking.
Как минимум возьмём английский и русский - это уже там штук 60, грубо говоря.
And every letter has to be drawn. You have to draw it so that it matches the other letters,
И каждую букву нужно отрисовать. Нарисовать так, чтобы она сочеталась с остальными буквами,
so that the text is more or less readable. And it's all quite a lot of complicated work,
чтобы более-менее воспринимался текст. И это всё достаточно объёмная сложная работа,
especially since I don't have a specific background in fonts.
особенно при условии, что у меня нет специфического образования для работы со шрифтами.
Lutzai: Wait, and you know all these languages more or less or how are you familiar with them?
Luțai: Погоди, а ты все эти языки знаешь более-менее или как ты с ними знакома?
Here's what I'm curious about. Since you've been reworking fonts, no?
Вот что мне интересно. Раз ты перерабатывала шрифты, нет?
Sophia: Roughly speaking, watching how it just looks in the draft and I've read articles on the subject,
Sofia: Грубо говоря, смотрела как это просто смотрится в рыбе и я читала статьи на эту тему,
and I found a couple books with all kinds of major core impressions.
и нашла пару книг со всякими главными основными впечатлениями.
The writing tradition for displaying a character is very important. It kind of defines how that
Традиция написания для отображения символа очень важна. Она как бы определяет как этот
symbol will look like. The simplest example is the letter "N" in English and "И" in Russian.
символ будет выглядеть. Самый простой пример - буква "N" английская и "И" русская.
If you just take the "N" and reflect it, it won't look like an "И" trivially because,
Если ты просто возьмёшь "N" и отразишь, она не будет выглядеть как "И" банально потому,
that there should be different thicknesses there. They were kind of spelled differently in their time. That's why we perceive it differently.
что там должны быть разные толщины. Их как бы по-разному писали в свою время. Поэтому мы воспринимаем её не так.
She looks like Ominous Valley, like a silly thing.
Она выглядит как Зловещая Долина, как глупость.
Lutzai: Here's what I'm wondering. How many times do you have to go through a game to get it neatly ported to another platform?
Luțai: Вот что мне интересно. А сколько раз надо пройти игру, чтобы аккуратно перенести её на другую платформу?
In my mind, to rework the user experience and add some new features to such an ancient project
В моём понимании, чтобы переработать пользовательский опыт и добавить какие-то новые фишки в такой древний проект
you have to take the game apart brick by brick, in reverse order. But is that really the case?
нужно сначала по кирпичику, в обратном порядке, разобрать игру на части. Но так ли это на самом деле?
Did you go through the whole game with Motion? Who did you make do it? You know, so everybody could test it.
А ты прошёл всю игру с Motion'ом? А кого ты заставил это делать? Ну чтобы все оттестировали.
Gleb: Irina did most of it. Yeah, she's probably already told you about her hard life.
Gleb: По большей части этим занималась Irina. Да, она уже, возможно, успела тебе нажаловаться на свою нелегкую жизнь.
No, no, no. She said to go to you and you tell me everything.
Luțai: Нет, нет, нет. Она сказала, что нужно пойти к тебе, и ты все расскажешь.
Do you actually have to go through the whole game like that to release a feature like that?
Вообще, чтобы в релиз такую фичу выпустить нужно всю игру так пройти?
Gleb: In general yes. Well, at least spend a lot of time testing it at all stages of the game.
Gleb: По большому счёту, да. Ну, по крайней мере, достаточно много времени уделить её тестированию на всех этапах игры.
Because, clearly, the same set of movements, it's at different stages of the game, depending on the hero's pumping,
Потому что, понятное дело, что один и тот же сет мувов, он на разных этапах игры, в зависимости от прокачки героя,
it's gonna feel very different.
будет ощущаться совсем по-разному.
Lutzai: Tell me, did you invent it or did you master it as well?
Luțai: Скажи, а ты её придумал или освоил в том числе тоже?
Gleb: Well it happened, in general, at the same time. We had several prototypes
Gleb: Ну это происходило, в общем-то, одновременно. У нас было несколько прототипов
we've been doing some testing within our team, collecting feedback.
мы проводили некое тестирование внутри нашей команды, собирали фидбеки.
And then implemented changes based on that. I'm the kind of game designer who thinks that basically every single
Ну и на основе этого внедряли изменения. Я из тех геймдизайнеров, которые придерживаются позиции, что в общем-то каждый
developer should be a game designer to the best of their ability. So my work on the project in that regard
разработчик в меру своих сил и возможностей должен быть геймдизайнером. То есть моя работа на проекте в этом плане
was more about getting people to cooperate with each other.
больше сводилась именно к кооперации людей между собой.
And just the fact that I probably have as much Gothic experience as all the other guys on our team combined.
И банально к тому, что у меня, пожалуй, опыта наигранно в Готике как у всех остальных ребят у нас в команде вместе взятых.
In the last six months I've probably spent 200 hours in the first one alone.
За последние полгода я, наверное, только в первой провёл часов 200. я не считала это точно больше 100 раз
Irina: I haven't counted. It's definitely more than 100 times. Lutzai: Really?
Irina: Я не считала. Это точно больше 100 раз. Luțai: Серьезно?
Irina: Maybe even more than that. I mean when I'm testing I'm not playing the game,
Irina: Может быть даже ещё больше. То есть когда я тестирую я не играю в игру,
and that's a little bit different. It's the other way around, I'm testing something, playing something, practicing something.
и это немножко не то. У меня наоборот задача проверить что-то, наиграть, отработать.
I already have some idea where it might break and I'm going through those places.
У меня уже есть какие-то домыслы где могло бы сломаться, и я по этим местечкам прохожу.
I feel like a detective trying to find the guilty person behind some kind of breakdown.
Я чувствую себя детективом, который пытается найти виновника какой-то поломки.
While testing Gothic, we got close. And we started making Gothic jokes. Lutzai: About Gomez, yeah, I heard that.
Тестируя Готику, мы с ней сблизились. И мы начали шутить шутками из Готики. Luțai: Про Гомеза да, я услышал.
Irina: There's a funny thing in the second one, when you drink the curse-removing potion,
Irina: Во второй есть забавная штука, когда ты выпиваешь зелье снимающее проклятие,
and it says, "You feel relieved." Every time I go on vacation, I send that picture.
и там надпись: "Вы чувствуете освобождение". Каждый раз, когда я ухожу в отпуск, я присылаю эту картинку.
Sophia: Honestly, I've only replayed Gothic once. Because I've watched quite a lot of
Sofia: Честно, в Готику я переигрывала только один раз. Потому что я довольно много пересмотрела всяких
streams where someone's playing. So I was mostly focused on the interface there.
стримов где кто-то играет. Поэтому я там в основном ориентировалась на интерфейс.
And I played myself to understand the player experience within the game.
А сама я играла, чтобы понять опыт игрока внутри игры.
Lutzai: I think it's hard to understand that from streams. Or am I wrong about that?
Luțai: Мне кажется, что по стримам это сложно оценить. Или я ошибаюсь?
Sofia: No, it's true. You're making all the right points. But I had Gothic as more than one project.
Sofia: Нет, это правда. Ты всё правильно говоришь. Но у меня Готика была не одним проектом.
So I didn't have enough time for multiple playthroughs, but one was generally enough for me.
Поэтому мне не хватило времени на несколько прохождений, но одного мне в целом хватило.
I think that's enough for me. Gothic isn't the smallest game after all.
Мне кажется, это достаточно. Готика игра всё-таки не самая маленькая.
And as you go through, you face challenges and understand the nuances of the controls.
И пока ты проходишь, ты сталкиваешься с трудностями и понимаешь нюансы управления.
[Eugene Grigorchuk. BG3 project manager on Mac] Lutzai: Wait a minute. So you were in charge of porting... Eugene Grigorchuk: Yeah.
[Евгений Григорчук. Руководитель проекта BG3 на Mac] Luțai: Погоди. То есть ты занимался портированием... Евгений Григорчук: Да.
Lutzai: But you didn't play Baldur's Gate? Eugene: Not at all.
Luțai: Но не играл в Baldur's Gate? Евгений: Вообще нет.
Lutskai: How does it work? Eugene: It's very simple.
Luțai: А как это работает? Евгений: Это очень просто.
Lutzai: So it's kind of unnecessary, right? Eugene: Yeah. So I haven't really played ELEX either. Here's the story I have.
Luțai: То есть типа не нужно, да? Евгений: Да. Так я и в ELEX не играл на самом деле. У меня вот какая история.
I got through DOS 2, I think, until the first act. Then things got busy.
Я DOS 2 прошёл, по-моему, до первого акта. Потом что-то дела были.
Then I started working. And I actually have 780 hours of Divinity on my Steam profile.
Потом уже работать стал. И собственно у меня в Divinity на моём Steam профиле наиграно 780 часов.
It's one of my most played games. I don't know anything about it.
Это одна из самых моих типа играемых игр. Я ничего о ней не знаю.
They tell me like this, roughly: there's a location, there's a problem on it, it needs to be fixed. I load the location and that's it.
Мне говорят так, условно: есть локация, на ней есть проблема - нужно исправить. Я загружаю локацию и всё.
Usually with quests, it's just you press a combination, roughly, of keys 1-3-4.
Обычно что касается квестов, там просто ты нажимаешь комбинацию, условно, клавиш 1-3-4.
It starts a cutscene, the right cutscene. And this is a cutscene, let's say it has graphical artifacts, I do a captcha right away
Начинается катсцена, нужная катсцена. И вот эта катсцена, допустим в ней графические артефакты, я сразу делаю капчу
and I start watching it. And that's it. I have no idea at all what...
и начинаю смотреть. И всё. Я вообще не представляю что...
Lutzai: So those are basically a list, specifically these tasks with the moments where to look for them, you're already correcting them. Eugene: Yeah, yeah.
Luțai: То есть те, по сути список, конкретно таких задач с моментами где их искать, ты их уже правишь. Евгений: Да, да.
Lutzai: And you're not very interested in these games yourself? Eugene: Baldur's Gate or all of them?
Luțai: А тебе самому эти игры не очень интересны? Евгений: Baldur's Gate или вообще все?
Lutsai: Well basically ELEX, Baldur's Gate, you know, what you're porting.
Luțai: Ну в принципе ELEX, Baldur's Gate, ну то что ты портируешь.
Eugene: I think I've seen all the locations in Baldur's Gate. I think... I don't know, I've seen a million of them and somehow... I'm just getting bored with it.
Евгений: Я уже по-моему все локации в Baldur's Gate видел. По-моему... Я не знаю, я видел миллион всего и как-то... ну уже надоедает просто.
Because you're with this 24-7 game. And you come home at night,
Потому что ты с этой игрой 24 на 7. И ты приходишь такой домой вечерком,
and you're like, "Man, I wish I had 10 more hours to look at the same thing."
такой: блин, ещё бы 10 часов посмотреть на одно и то же.
Lutzai: All right, come on, show some skill. You know these mechanics like the back of your hand.
Luțai: Ну хорошо, давай, покажи класс. Ты же знаешь эту механику как свои пять пальцев.
Well you showed him, yeah. Very good.
Ну ты показал ему, да. Очень в тему.
No, that was impressive. All right, don't bother. Somebody's gonna do it for sure. On the mats, they're going to go through the...
Не, это было впечатляюще. Ладно, не мучайся. Кто-то стопудов так и пройдёт. На ковриках проходят всяких там...
Gleb: He'll thank you, yeah. Lutzai: Yes! That's actually a reason to do a challenge.
Gleb: Ещё и спасибо скажет, да. Luțai: Да! Это на самом деле повод для челленджа.
In the game:"Your blood! Don't do it again."
В игре: Твоя кровь! Больше не делай этого.
Lutzai: What is the uniqueness of Gothic's design in your opinion?
Luțai: В чём заключается уникальность дизайна Готики на твой взгляд?
Reinhard: We really put a lot of thought into it when we started working on the Gothic 1 Remake.
Reinhard: Мы действительно много думали над этим, когда начали работать над ремейком.
The game has a certain atmosphere because of the way the world and the characters are designed. And the main feature of the game
В игре складывается определённая атмосфера благодаря тому как спроектирован мир и персонажи. И основная особенность игры
is that it doesn't manipulate you for the sake of keeping you, but it prioritizes player agentivity.
заключается в том, что она не манипулирует тобой ради удержания, но ставит на первое место агентивность игрока.
So the player's decisions matter. And he needs to interact with the world to make sense of what's going on.
Поэтому решения игрока имеют значение. И ему нужно взаимодействовать с миром, чтобы разобраться в происходящем.
The same thing applies to the simulation of a world where every NPC has their own routines and their own activities that
Это же касается симуляции мира, в котором у каждого NPC есть свой распорядок дня и свои занятия, которые
fill that world with life. I think that's one of the main reasons why these games were so popular and unique.
наполняют этот мир жизнью. Я думаю, это одна из основных причин, почему эти игры были так популярны и уникальны.
Lutzai: But where does the agentivity of Gothic come from? And the completely unconventional approach to even some of the
Luțai: Но откуда взялась вот эта агентивность Готики? И абсолютно нестандартный подход даже к каким-то
little things that make the game handle and feel differently than other games. You hear the phrase quite often nowadays,
мелочам из-за которых игра управляется и ощущается иначе нежели другие игры. Вот сейчас можно услышать фразу довольно часто,
that Unreal games feel the same. Or, "These guys should change their engine, otherwise their future games
мол, игры на Unreal ощущаются одинаковыми. Или: вот этим ребятам пора бы поменять движок, иначе их будущие
will stop developing. And the heroes of this issue have an interesting point of view on this matter.
проекты остановятся в развитии. И у героев этого выпуска любопытная точка зрения на этот счёт.
Why, in these times of technical limitations, could they make such an elaborate one on different levels
Почему в такие времена технических ограничений могли сделать настолько проработанную на разных уровнях
game where a large number of all sorts of systems worked. Again, as you rightly said, a closed world, but
игру, где работало большое количество всевозможных систем. Опять же, как вы правильно сказали, замкнутый мир, но
that felt alive. Why did something like that stop being done afterward? It's like there's no examples.
который ощущался при этом живым. Почему подобное перестали делать после? Как будто и примеров нет.
Platon: I wonder about that myself. This is one of the topics that we often talk about with Mr. Reinhard.
Platon: Я сам удивляюсь. Это одна из тем, о которых мы часто говорим с господином Рейнхардом.
How is it that here Gothic was able to do that? I know how Gothic works, I know what's in there,
Как так что вот Готика это смогла? Я знаю как устроена Готика, я знаю что там,
like, 50% of the game is scripting, yeah. That's no secret either. 50% of the game is scripting in a very advanced language,
например, 50% игры - это скрипты, да. Это тоже не секрет. 50% игры - это скрипты на очень продвинутом языке,
which, by the way, is the crown jewel of Gothic, no doubt about it.
который, кстати, прям жемчужина Готики, без сомнений.
The local scripting language, Dedaulus it's called. I believe the colleagues at Piranha Bytes
Местный скриптовый язык, Dedaulus он называется. Полагаю, что у коллег из Piranha Bytes
had a real epiphany. It was... well maybe it was from above, yeah.
тогда было настоящее озарение. Это было... ну возможно это свыше, да.
How delicate the player was being led to some things: when he was looking for that crossbow,
Как тонко игрока подводили к некоторым вещам: когда он искал этот арбалет,
a classic example from your own video, I think. That famous one with the Chromanin. Even when I was playing,
классический пример из вашего же по-моему ролика. Вот этот знаменитый с Хроманином. Даже, когда я играл,
I felt like I was totally involved in the whole thing. And I guess the guys at that time were very good and
я чувствовал, что я полностью вовлечен в это всё. И полагаю, что ребята тогда очень хорошо и
strongly thought it through. And also, probably, I think probably in those days people weren't afraid to say you have to do it this way.
сильно продумывали это. И ещё, скорее всего, я думаю в те времена люди не боялись говорить, что надо сделать так.
Like I want that when I'm running and there's a herd of wolves hovering behind me, all sheep
Типа я хочу, что когда я бегу, а за мной висит стадо волков, то все овцы
would run away and the NPCs with axes would lunge at the wolves. And the wolves would start running away,
разбегались, а NPC с топорами бросались на волков. А волки начинали убегать,
and they'd run into the houses and they'd attack the locals. And nobody ever said, "Oh, that's too hard,
забегали в дома и грызли местное население. И никто тогда не говорил: "О, это слишком сложно,
You've got to build a neural network." Everybody just sat there and did it.
Тут нужно построить нейросеть". Все просто сидели и делали.
And sometimes using simple old methods. Roughly speaking, if a wolf sees a hut,
И иногда и довольно-таки кондовыми методами. Грубо говоря, если волк видит хатку,
then run into the hut. There you go. Of course, Gothic can be breached, and there's no
то забежать в хатку. Ну вот так. Конечно, Готику можно проломить, и никакого там
super-praised AI inside. But the way the AI is done is still a head above,
супер хвалёного AI внутри нет. Но то, как сделан AI всё равно получается на голову выше,
than it is in today's reality. I think it's very useful for the younger generation to see,
чем в современных-то реалиях. Я прям считаю, что очень полезно будет молодому поколению увидеть,
an example of how the old Gothic works, how games can be made.
на примере того как работает старая Готика, как могут делать игры.
Konstantine: When I look at Gothic's code, I don't see anything complicated about it.
Konstantin: Когда я смотрю код Готики, я не вижу ничего сложного в нём.
Even later on, Piranha Bytes' code became more complicated, they became more professional, and this simplicity
Уже впоследствии в коде Piranha Bytes появилось усложнение, они стали профессиональнее, и вот эта простота
has gone a little bit. I think it's such a unique moment when a new rock band is born and they have a
немножко ушла. Мне кажется, это такой уникальный момент, когда рождается новая рок-группа, у неё выходит
first album. They are so fresh, trying everything, interested in everything.
первый альбом. Она такая со свежими силами, она всё пробует, ей всё интересно.
And in that moment, with literally simple tools, they create a masterpiece. It's the same here. Guys with ambition,
И в этот момент, буквально простыми инструментами, она создаёт шедевр. Вот здесь тоже самое. Ребята с амбициями,
they didn't put any blocks, any limits on themselves. They just did whatever they wanted to do. Yeah, then the publisher put those restrictions,
не стали ставить себе блоки, ограничения. Они просто делали всё, что хотели. Да, потом эти ограничения издатель поставил,
and they had to cut something out. But the energy of this young rock band, you can feel it in Piranha. Even if we
и нужно было что-то вырезать. Но сам заряд вот этой молодой рок-группы, он в Пираньях чувствуется. Даже вот если мы
look at some of their early pictures. It's just, I don't know, Metallica! They have such drive.
посмотрим их ранние фотографии. Это просто, не знаю, Металлика! От них идёт такой драйв.
What's special about their engine is that the entire terrain is rendered polygonally.
Особенность их движка в том, что весь террейн рендерится пополигонально.
This is not very good from an optimization point of view.
Это не очень хорошо с точки зрения оптимизации.
But in terms of the logic of the world, how they laid that logic down, it makes it feel of the world,
Но с точки зрения логики мира, как они его закладывали эту логику, это делает ощущение от мира,
That it's really so composite. It's like a constructor is made. We can see that in the textures,
что он действительно такой составной. Он как конструктор сделан. Мы это можем наблюдать по текстурам,
we can see it in the way the parts of the world are built in. The forests are quite elegantly done,
мы можем наблюдать это по тому, как встроены части мира. Достаточно изящно сделаны леса,
which are actually enclosed rooms. They're literally rooms that you walk into.
которые на самом деле являются закрытыми помещениями. Это буквально комнаты, куда ты заходишь.
So they don't have anything mediocre. They have something that's all their own, unique, special.
То есть у них нету ничего посредственного. У них всё что-то такое своё, уникальное, особенное.
They've left such courage in every decision they've made.
Они оставили такую смелость в каждом своём решении.
Eugene: ELEX was written by about five people, as for the rendering, I think it was either five or three. And all the guys were
Евгений: ELEX писали примерно пять человек, что касается рендера, по-моему, то ли пять, то ли три. И все парни были
ultra smart. You can just see it in their code. You see the code, you see how it's written. You realize, if you want
ультра толковые. Это просто по их коду видно. Ты видишь код, ты видишь как он написан. Ты понимаешь, чтобы тебе
to port this project, you can even not touch certain files at all. It's amazing. They're so
спортировать этот проект, ты можешь вообще определённые файлы никогда не трогать. Это удивительно. Они настолько
overflowing in their knowledge of writing code that they did a plus or minus perfect rendering, to be honest.
преисполнились в своём познании написания кода, что они сделали плюс-минус идеальный рендеринг, если быть честным.
Lutzai: Do you enjoy on the tasks themselves, the code itself? The way it's done? Evgeny: From the code itself, yes.
Luțai: Ты кайфуешь от самих задач, от самого кода? От того как он сделан? Евгений: От самого кода, да.
I spent most of ELEX'a in twenty files or so.
Я большую часть ELEX'a провёл в двадцати файлах или около того.
I kind of knew them by heart and so on. And that's basically how the rendering itself works, you know,
Я типа знал их наизусть и так далее. И вот в принципе как сам рендеринг устроен, ты понимаешь,
that it's pretty awesome.
что это это вообще офигенно.
Lutzai: As you've realized, Piranha Bytes at one time tried to make everything from scratch,
Luțai: Как вы уже поняли, Piranha Bytes в своё время пытались всё сделать с нуля,
without which we might not have gotten these unique games. But there's a downside.
без чего мы возможно не получили бы эти уникальные игры. Но есть и обратная сторона.
of console and PC players differed dramatically. Even that they couldn't get to know the classics
консольных и ПК игроков кардинально различался. Вплоть до того, что они банально не могли познакомиться с классикой
from a different platform. And even years later, this situation is not easily changeable. And some projects may not be able to
с другой платформы. И даже спустя годы эту ситуацию не так уж просто исправить. А некоторые проекты вообще могут
come back to life.
так никогда и не воскреснуть.
Does a game like this, even though it's on Switch, still need to be optimized?
Нужно ли такую игру, хоть и на Switch, но всё же оптимизировать?
Platon: Gothic is a very unoptimized game. It's a hell of an unoptimized game.
Platon: Готика очень неоптимизированная игра. Она адски неоптимизированная игра.
We've been thinking about this for a very long time. Gothic 1 on Switch the first day we launched it,
Мы очень долго думали над этим. Готика 1 на Switch'e в первый день, когда мы её запустили,
in the world it was nine frames per second. Nine frames because
в мире там было девять кадров в секунду. Девять кадров, потому что
of the CPU eating everything. If we compare the history of CPU growth,
почти всё время выедал центральный процессор. Если мы будем сравнивать историю роста процессоров,
their performance on a PC, we see that we had single-core configurations first,
их мощностей на ПК, то мы увидим, что сначала у нас были одноядерные конфигурации,
that were going up in frequency very quickly. We'll remember these pentiums right here.
которые очень быстро поднимали частоту. Мы вспомним вот эти пентиумы.
And if we look at the time when Gothic came out, it was the heyday of single core systems.
И если мы посмотрим в какое время вышла Готика, то это был расцвет одноядерных систем.
They had to have a lot of purity, they ran pretty fast. But the game was not multithreaded at all.
У них должна была быть большая чистота, они работали довольно быстро. Но игра была совершенно не многопоточная.
So it didn't talk about any multithreaded stuff at all, not at all.
То есть ни о каких там многопоточных вещах в ней не говорилось вообще, от слова совсем.
Actually, Gothic is based on the Quake engine. A la Quake.
Вообще Готика построена на движке Quake. Ну а-ля Quake.
The game takes, it bites the triangles. In fact, the whole world is made of triangles in computer graphics.
Игра берёт, она обкусывает треугольники. Вообще весь мир строится из треугольников в компьютерной графике.
It's nibbling on triangles that don't fit on the screen. And it goes through a giant tree quite quickly.
Она обкусывает треугольники, которые не попадают в экран. А проходится она по гигантскому дереву довольно быстро.
And the CPU has enough power to to get around all
И у центрального процессора хватает мощности, чтобы быстро
these triangles fast that it throws at the video card. That approach is not applicable in a modern video card.
обойти все эти треугольники, которые она бросает в видеокарту. В современной видеокарте этот подход неприменим.
We can't throw a huge amount of geometry into the video card every frame.
Мы не можем каждый кадр бросать огромное количество геометрии в видеокарту.
It's just kind of outdated. And modern graphics cards are optimized for something else.
Это просто как-то уже устарело. Да и современные видеокарты оптимизированы под другое.
They're optimized that the geometry lies on top of them. We were shocked.
Они оптимизированы, что геометрия лежит на них. Мы были в шоке.
The game spent all its time doing tree avoidance, clipping triangles, working with AI and all that.
Игра всё своё время занималась обходом деревьев, отстриганием треугольников, работой с AI и все такое.
And naturally on that same thread, on that same process, she was loading its resources.
И естественно на этой же thread'ине, на этом же процессе она загружала свои ресурсы.
So the program was immediately clear - rewrite.
Поэтому сразу была понятна программа - переписывать.
Rewrite and parallelize as many things as possible. First, understandably,
Переписывать и параллелить как можно больше вещей. Первым, понятное дело,
things that are obviously subject to parallelization are resource loading and sound.
параллелизму подверглись вещи, которые очевидно подвергаются параллелизации - это загрузка ресурсов и звук.
Well then beyond that, so far we've been working on making the approach to rendering in Gothic really different.
Ну а потом уж дальше, до сих пор мы работаем над тем, чтобы сделать подход к рендерингу в Готике по-настоящему другим.
[Rostislav Mikheev. Elverils Lead Graphics Engineer] So let's say you get your dose of some of that satisfaction when you are
[Ростислав Михеев. Ведущий инженер по графике Elverils] Так скажем, ты получаешь свою дозу какую-то вот этого удовлетворения, когда ты
solving these problems anyway. And you find a bunch of these bugs along with it.
в любом случае эти проблемы решаешь. И за компанию с этим, еще находишь кучу этих багов.
There's always some offsets in memory through manual calculations
Постоянно какие-нибудь там оффсеты в памяти через ручные калькуляции
of some magical numbers: something is adding up and trying to get somewhere. And you realize it's not going to be at all
каких-то магических чисел: что-то складывается и куда-то пытается залезть. И ты понимаешь, что это вообще не будет
work ever again. That's unrealistic on a CPU nowadays. So there's a thrill in it all.
работать больше никогда. В настоящее время на CPU такое нереально. Поэтому в этом во всём свой кайф есть.
Lutzai: Did you remaster the soundtrack of the original Gothic? Did Kai Rosenkranz himself do that?
Luțai: Вы отремастерили саундтрек оригинальной Готики? Этим занимался сам Kai Rosenkranz?
Reinhard: Kai Rosenkranz created the original soundtrack. He consulted with the developers of Gothic Classic, as the
Reinhard: Kai Rosenkranz создал оригинальный саундтрек. Он консультировал разработчиков Gothic Classic, так как
technically the music and the soundtrack is done in a very strange way. It's different from other games that work with MP3 or WAV
технически музыка и саундтрек сделана очень странным образом. Это отличается от других игр, которые работают с MP3 или WAV
files that are played in the background and then dynamically mixed with other files. There is no such synchronization here.
файлами, которые воспроизводятся на фоне, а затем динамически смешиваются с другими файлами. Здесь нет такой синхронизации.
There's a melody and a score, and then the music is played on the fly by virtual instruments. And in the actual
Есть мелодия и партитура, а затем музыка воспроизводится на лету виртуальными инструментами. И в самой
original PC version of Gothic an outdated DirectX library called DirectX is used
оригинальной версии Готики на ПК используется устаревшая библиотека DirectX под названием DirectX Music.
This technology is a thing of the past. So we had to recreate a similar playback logic, and Kai played
Эта технология ушла в прошлое. Поэтому нам пришлось воссоздать аналогичную логику воспроизведения, и Кай сыграл в этом
a huge role in that. Making sure everything sounded right. We still have some problems with the technology.
огромную роль. Контролировал, чтобы всё звучало правильно. У нас до сих пор есть некоторые проблемы с технологией.
For example, sometimes there are not smooth transitions. And yes, on top of that, Kai Rosenkranz is a member of the Alkimia Interactive team,
Например, иногда происходят резкие переходы. И да, кроме того, Kai Rosenkranz - член команды Alkimia Interactive,
that's working on the Remake. So in all the trailers and stuff that we're releasing,
которая работает над ремейком. Так что во всех трейлерах и прочих материалах, которые мы выпускаем,
he's the driving force and the real maestro of sound that's doing all of this.
он главная движущая сила и настоящий маэстро звука, который всем этим занимается.
Platon: The structure of the music file, it's known.
Platon: Структура музыкального файла, она известна.
We can clearly understand it, how the music file is structured.
Мы можем её чётко понять, как устроен музыкальный файл.
Then the instruments from which the music of the Gothic itself is formed. We can isolate the instruments.
Потом инструменты из которых формируется сама музыка Готики. Мы можем выделить инструменты.
We can convert them into a format that we're comfortable with for Switch. We've done that. And then we need to do the synthesizer.
Мы можем их переделать в формат, который удобен нам для Switch'a. Мы это сделали. Ну и потом нам нужно сделать синтезатор.
A little software synthesizer. It used to be very popular. The kind of music that plays in Gothic on Switch
Маленький программный синтезатор. Раньше он был очень популярен. Та музыка, которая играет в Готике на Switch'e -
is completely, completely different from the music that plays on Windows. Although it is similar, very similar,
совершенно, абсолютно не та музыка, которая играет на Windows. Хотя она и похожа, очень похожа,
because we've tried to make it as similar as possible. But there's still room for improvement.
потому что мы старались сделать её как можно похожей. Но всё равно там есть куда улучшать.
Lutzai: As a player, this is a pretty frustrating topic for me. If you watched my video about sound in games, for example.
Luțai: Как для игрока, для меня это довольно обидная тема. Если вы, например, смотрели мое видео про звук в играх
Thief series, you'll remember that I talked about using the same EAX technology that Platon mentioned in the beginning
серии Thief, то помните, что я рассказывал об использовании той самой технологии EAX, которую упоминал Platon в самом начале
of the video. There, it was used to navigate the level without a map or any locators. But unfortunately,
ролика. Там с её помощью можно было ориентироваться на уровне без карты и каких-либо локаторов. Но, к сожалению,
the development culture now is set up so that instead of preserving and developing the really cool technologies which
культура разработки сейчас устроена так, что вместо сохранения и развития действительно крутых технологий, которые
give a unique gaming experience, the industry is trying to optimize and cheapen the processes with unified
дарят уникальный игровой опыт, индустрия стремится оптимизировать и удешевить процессы с помощью унифицированных
engines with off-the-shelf solutions. That's great, I guess. But you end up with an average toolkit because of which,
движков с готовыми решениями. Наверное, это здорово. Но в итоге получается средний инструментарий из-за которого,
in my opinion, it's less and less likely that you're going to get a wow effect from games. And against that backdrop, ancient projects feel fresh.
по моему мнению, всё реже испытываешь какой-то вау-эффект от игр. И на этом фоне древние проекты ощущаются свежо.
Konstantin: Because technology is becoming unified, a different paradigm starts to prevail.
Konstantin: Из-за того, что технологии становятся унифицированными, начинает превалировать другая парадигма.
You don't need to do everything yourself. You just need to utilize what's available to everybody.
Тебе не нужно всё делать самому. Тебе достаточно пользоваться наработками, доступными для всех.
And you end up in a situation where you're trying to build something unique from a publicly available constructor.
И ты оказываешься в ситуации, что ты пытаешься строить что-то уникальное из общедоступного конструктора.
Yeah, the constructor can let you do some unique things, but that uniqueness is limited
Да, конструктор может тебе позволить сделать какие-то уникальные вещи, но эта уникальность ограничена
not only by the constructor itself, but by the list of things that you can make with it.
не только самим конструктором, но и перечнем того, что из него можно сделать.
We got into a sort of confined box where we explored everything pretty quickly.
Мы попали в некий ограниченный короб, где мы достаточно быстро всё исследовали.
It's still the same aquarium that you're put in and you can't go outside of it. And so when I, for example,
Всё тот же аквариум, в который тебя поместили, а за него выйти ты не можешь. И вот когда я, например,
when I start Gothic, first of all, I have this amazing feeling that I'm not in this aquarium.
запускаю Готику, у меня прежде всего потрясающее ощущение от того, что я не в этом аквариуме.
I'm somewhere outside. Creativity basically starts with a technical solution. The Piranhas had exactly that.
Я где-то снаружи. Творчество в принципе начинается с технического решения. У Пираний было именно так.
And I think that's the secret to success, that you're consistent not from some stage:
И я думаю это и есть секрет успеха, что ты последователен не с какого-то этапа:
now I'm just going to take what I've got, and now I'm going to do something individual. But when you
вот сейчас я просто возьму что есть, а вот теперь я буду делать что-то индивидуальное. А когда ты
individualized at all from the beginning. That's exactly the lost path that gamemade needs right now.
индивидуален вообще с самого начала. Как раз тот потерянный путь, который геймдеву нужен сейчас.
[Authors: Alexei Lutzai, Konstantin Timofeev. Editing, photography: Alexei Lutzai]
[Авторы: Aleksei Luțai, Konstantin Timofeev. Монтаж, съемка: Aleksei Luțai]
[Starfield post credits] Rostislav: it's a very interesting story. We once at one time,
[Байка после титров про Starfield] Ростислав: это очень интересная история. Мы как-то одно время,
in between, we worked with someone who was known in GPU circles, Wolfgang Engel.
в промежутке, работали с одним человеком, известным в узких GPU кругах, Wolfgang Engel.
GPU Gems he wrote books that just taught people how to write modern graphics.
GPU Gems он книги писал, которые как раз учили людей как графику современную писать.
Platon: For GPU programmers he is a god. Rostislav: Well, I guess so.
Platon: Для GPU-программистов он прям бог. Ростислав: Ну, наверное, так даже.
Here, and he was developing his own graphics solution. It was called The Forge. We worked with him once,
Вот, и он занимался разработкой собственного решения графического. Называлось оно The Forge. Как-то мы с ним поработали,
worked with him, and then we finished. We put a lot of stuff in there for Mac. Platon: And for Switch even. Rostislav: We were also putting something for Switch.
поработали, расстались. Мы под Mac много туда очень впихивали. Platon: И под Switch даже. Ростислав: И под Switch что-то впихивали.
Wolfgang and I parted on some condition that we had some difficulties with time, and he was not happy with it.
Расстались мы с Вольфгангом с каким-то условием что у нас было все сложно со временем, его это не устраивало.
And they made a game on it afterward, hack-n-slash. Plato: Hades. Rostislav: Hades, right. Platon: Thank you.
И сделали они после этого на нем игру, hack-n-slash. Platon: Hades. Ростислав: Hades, точно. Спасибо.
And then they did a render for No Man's Sky on it. And then they did a render for Starfield on it as well.
А вот потом они сделали рендер для No Man's Sky на нем. И потом они сделали рендер для Starfield'а на нём же.
So the story is that yes, in Starfield and No Man's Sky there is
Поэтому история в том, что да, в Starfield и No Man's Sky
a graphical piece of The Forge that's actually the same render.
есть графический кусок The Forge, который на самом деле один и тот же рендер.
And there's still bits of our code in there somewhere. Platon: It's funny that Bethesda obviously didn't make a Mac version.
И где-то там ещё остались кусочки нашего кода. Platon: Прикольно, что Bethesda очевидно Mac версию не сделала.
I opened No Man's Sky, and what did I find inside? My work that I was writing.
А вот No Man's Sky я потрошил, и что я там нашёл внутри? Мой класс, который я писал.
Rostislav: Ah, yes, this one is a window creator. Lutzai: It's funny that Starfield gets blamed for this,
Ростислав: А, да, вот этот создания окошек. Luțai: Забавно ,что при этом Starfield обвиняют в том,
that No Man's Sky did pretty well. So they actually have more kinship than they might seem.
что у No Man's Sky получилось неплохо. То есть у них на самом деле больше родства, чем могло бы показаться.
Rostislav: Well, assuming that No Man's Sky was on iOS or Mac,
Ростислав: Ну там с допущением, что No Man's Sky вроде под iOS'ом был или под Mac'ом,
But then it's kind of, as I understand it, they kind of absorbed it more there. But that's, unfortunately,
но потом вроде, как понимаю, они его впитали там у себя больше. Но это, к сожалению,
I can't say for sure anymore. But they have a certain kinship, sure.
я точно уже не могу сказать. Но родство у них определённое есть, короче.
Platon: Yes, it's funny, funny. Rostislav: That's the story.
Platon: Да, прикольно, прикольно. Ростислав: Вот такая история.